so let's look at the problem of alas
sing in the virtually index physically
tagged caches this is our virtual
address and the way we access the cach
is these are the offset bits this would
be our index bits and this would be the
tag if we use this to access the cache
in a virtually indexed cache we use the
index part of the address from the
virtual address the rest comes from the
physical address but how do we form the
physical address well some lower bits of
the virtual address will be the page
offset the rest will be the page number
and now remember that the page number
gets translated to become the frame
number in the physical address while the
page offset just goes and becomes the
least significant bits of the physical
address and in a virtually indexed
physically tagged cache our tag comes
from here but our index came from here
so that we could begin the aess quickly
the thing to note is that the index bits
are relatively close to the list
significant bit of the virtual address
and that the page offset has a number of
bits so for a small cache it can happen
that the index bits that we used all
come from the page offset which means
they're the same as if we took them from
the physical address so although we are
indexing using the virtual address in
reality we are actually using the same
index that we would be using if we were
using the physical address which means
there would be no aliasing how is there
no alas syn
well because the virtual pages that have
different page numbers that map to the
same frame number can only differ in the
page number but they have to have the
same offset for the same data and
because only the offset matters for the
index if the index is low enough here
what happens is pretty much all of the
data that can possibly be in the same
place in the physical memory has to be
in the same set because the index is
determined only from the part that has
to be the same so we have that there is
no alas sync if all of the index bits
that we use came from the page offset
because really those are the same index
bits that would come from the physical
address if we had the physical index
cache we like this very much but the
cash has to be small enough to do this
so for example if we have a 4 kilobyte
page we would have a 12bit page offset
if our cache has a 32 byte block it has
a 5bit block offset here that means that
the index which still needs to fit in
the 12 bits of the page offset can only
have seven bits so we can only have 128
sets in this cache which limits its size
if we have more sets than this then some
of the index bits here come from the
page number and that changes when we
have the frame number so it can easily
be that the differ in these bits here
end up mapping to the same frame number
which we don't want because that means
that multiple sets in the cache could
have the same actual data which is bad
because we cannot find it then